<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The humble petition of the right honourable the lord mayor, aldermen, and commons of the city of London, in common-council assembled on the thirteenth of January, 1680 to the King's most Excellent Majesty, for the sitting of this present Parliament prorogu'd to the twentieth instant : together with the resolutions, orders, and debates of the said court.</title>
            <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45069</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3577</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12865</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11696725</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11696725</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48236</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45069)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48236)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 538:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The humble petition of the right honourable the lord mayor, aldermen, and commons of the city of London, in common-council assembled on the thirteenth of January, 1680 to the King's most Excellent Majesty, for the sitting of this present Parliament prorogu'd to the twentieth instant : together with the resolutions, orders, and debates of the said court.</title>
                  <author>City of London (England). Court of Common Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 11 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Samuel Roycroft ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>London (England) --  Politics and government.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48236:1"/>
            <p>THE HUMBLE PETITION OF THE RIGHT HONOURABLE THE Lord Mayor, ALDERMEN, AND Commons of the City of <hi>London,</hi> IN Common-Council Aſſembled, ON THE Thirteenth of <hi>January,</hi> 1680. To the King's moſt Excellent Majeſty, for the Sitting of this preſent Parliament Prorogu'd to the Twentieth Inſtant.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER With the RESOLUTIONS, ORDERS, and DEBATES of the ſaid COURT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> Printer to the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable City of <hi>London.</hi> 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:48236:2"/>
            <p>IT is Agreed and Ordered by this Court, That the Petition now Agreed on to be Preſented to His Majeſty, and ſuch Orders and Proceedings of this Court had this Day, as the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor ſhall think fit, ſhall after the ſaid Petition Preſented, be printed by ſuch Perſon as his Lordſhip ſhall Appoint.</p>
            <p>Purſuant to which Order, and to prevent falſe Copies, I do appoint <hi>Samuel Roycroft,</hi> Printer to this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable City, to print this Petition, with all the Orders and Debates thereupon; and that no other Perſon preſume to print the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>P. Ward</hi> Mayor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:48236:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:48236:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48236:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Commune Concil' tent' in Camera <hi>Guildhall</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitatis <hi>London</hi> Die Jovis decimo tertio die Januarij Anno Domini <hi>1680.</hi> Annoque Regni Domini noſtri <hi>Carol'</hi> Secundi nunc Regis <hi>Angl'</hi> &amp;c. Triceſimo ſecundo, coram <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent' Ward</hi> Mil', Major' Civitatis <hi>London, Thoma Aleyn</hi> Mil' &amp; Barr', <hi>Johanne Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick</hi> Mil', <hi>Johanne Lawrence</hi> Mil', <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio Waterman</hi> Mil', <hi>Joſepho Sheldon</hi> Mil', <hi>Jacobo Edwards</hi> Mil', &amp; <hi>Roberto Clayton</hi> Mil', Aldermannis, <hi>Georgio Treby</hi> Ar' Recordatore dicte Civit', <hi>Johanne Moore</hi> Mil', <hi>Willielmo Pritchard</hi> Mil', <hi>Henrico Tulſe</hi> Mil', <hi>Jacobo Smith</hi> Mil', <hi>Roberto Jeffery</hi> Mil', <hi>Johanne Shorter</hi> Mil', <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Gould</hi> Mil', <hi>Willielmo Rawſterne</hi> Mil', <hi>Thoma Beckford</hi> Mil', <hi>Johanne Chapman</hi> Mil', <hi>Simone Lewis</hi> Mil', <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pilkington</hi> Ar' Ald'ris, &amp; <hi>Henrico Corniſh</hi> Ar' Ald'ro ac unum Vicecom' dicte Civitatis necnon Major' parte Comminarior' dicte Civitatis in Communi Concil' tune &amp; ibidem Aſſemblat'.</head>
            <p>THIS Day the Members that ſerve for this City in Parliament, having com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated unto this Court a Vote or Reſolution of the Honourable Houſe of Commons, whereby that Houſe was pleaſed to give Thanks unto this City for their manifeſt Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty to the King, their Care, Charge, and Vigilance for the Preſervation of his Majeſties Perſon, and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48236:4"/>of the Proteſtant Religion. This Court is greatly ſenſible of the Honour thereby given to this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, And do declare, That it is the fixt and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form Reſolution of this City to perſevere in what they have done, and to contribute their utmoſt Aſſiſtance for the Defence of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, His Majeſties Perſon, and the Government Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>It was now unanimouſly Agreed and Ordered by this Court, That the Thanks of this Court be given to the Members that ſerve for this City in Parliament, for their good Service done this City, and their Faithfulneſs in diſcharging their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in that Honourable and great Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly.</p>
            <p>Upon a Petition now Preſented by divers Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens and Inhabitants of this City, repreſenting their Fears from the Deſigns of the Papiſts and their Adherents, and praying this Court to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint his Majeſty therewith, And to deſire, That the Parliament may ſit from the Day to which it ſtands Prorogued, until they have ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently provided againſt Popery and Arbitrary Power. This Court, after ſome Debate and Conſideration had thereupon, did return the Petitioners Thanks for their Care and good Intention herein; And did thereupon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate and appoint Sir <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Knights and Aldermen, Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Player</hi> Kt. Mr. <hi>John Du Bois, John Ellis</hi>
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> and Mr. <hi>Michael Godfrey</hi> Commoners, to withdraw, and immediately to prepare a Petition to his Majeſty upon the Subject matter of the ſaid Petition; who accordingly withdrawing, after ſome time returned again to this Court, and then preſented the Draught of ſuch a Petition
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48236:4"/>to his Majeſty. The Tenor whereof followeth, <hi>Viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="order">
               <head>To the Kings most Excellent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>After reading whereof, It is Agreed and Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by this Court <hi>(Nemine Contradicente)</hi> That the ſaid Petition ſhall be Preſented to his Majeſty this Evening, or as ſoon as conveniently may be. And the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor is deſired to preſent the ſame, accompanied with Sir <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> Sir <hi>Joſeph Sheldon,</hi> Sir <hi>James Edwards,</hi> Knights and Aldermen, Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> Deputy <hi>Hawes,</hi> Deputy <hi>Daniel, John Nichols, John Ellis,</hi> Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, Mr. <hi>Godfrey,</hi> and Capt. <hi>Griffith</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who are now nominated and appointed to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon his Lordſhip at the Preſenting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:48236:5"/>
            <head>Ward Mayor.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Commune Concil' tent'</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>13<hi rend="sup">tio</hi> Januarij 1680. Annoque Regis</hi> Car. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">di</hi> 32<hi rend="sup">do</hi>.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>IT is Agreed and Ordered by this Court, <hi>(Nemine Contradicente)</hi> That the Humble Petition to His Majeſty from this Court, now read and agreed upon, ſhall be Preſented to His Majeſty this Evening, or as ſoon as conveniently may be. And the Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable the Lord Mayor is deſired to Preſent the ſame, accompanied with Sir <hi>John Lawrence,</hi> Sir <hi>Joſeph Sheldon,</hi> and Sir <hi>James Edwards</hi> Knights and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen, Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> Deputy <hi>Hawes,</hi> Deputy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, John Nicholls, John Ellis,</hi> Eſquires, Mr. <hi>Godfrey, and</hi> Capt. Griffith, <hi>Commoners, who are now nominated and appointed to attend upon his Lordſhip at the Preſenting thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:48236:5"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST Excellent MAJESTY.</head>
            <head type="sub">The Humble PETITION of the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Commons of the City of <hi>LONDON,</hi> in Common Council Aſſembled.</head>
            <opener>Moſt Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
            <p>THat Your Majeſties great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil in Parliament, having in their late Seſſion, in purſuance of Your Majeſties Direction, entred upon a ſtrict and impartial Inquiry into the horrid and execrable Popiſh Plot,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48236:6"/>which hath been for ſeveral years laſt paſt, and ſtill is, carried on for deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Your Majeſties Sacred Perſon and Government, and extirpation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the utter Ruine of Your Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects; and having ſo far proceeded therein, as juſtly to attaint upon full Evidence one of the Five Lords impeached for the ſame, and were in further Proſecution of the remaining Four Lords, and other Conſpirators therein.</p>
            <p>And as well the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, as the Commons in Your ſaid Parliament aſſembled having Declared, That they are fully ſatisfied, that there now is, and for divers years laſt paſt, hath been a horrid and Treaſonable Plot and Conſpiracy contrived and carried on by thoſe of the Popiſh Religion in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> for Maſſacring the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the Proteſtant Religion, and the Ancient eſtabliſhed Government of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And Your ſaid Commons having Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peached the Earl of <hi>Tyrone,</hi> in order to the bringing him to Juſtice for the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48236:6"/>ſame; And having under Examination other Conſpirators in the ſaid <hi>Iriſh</hi> Plot.</p>
            <p>And Your ſaid Commons having likewiſe impeached Sir <hi>William Scroggs,</hi> Chief Juſtice of Your Majeſties Court of Kings Bench, for Treaſon and other great Crimes and Miſdemeanors in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſubvert the Laws of this Kingdom by his Arbitrary and Illegal proceedings; And having voted Impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt ſeveral other Judges for the like Miſdemeanors.</p>
            <p>Your Petitioners conſidering the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Hazards to which Your Sacred Life, and the Proteſtant Religion, and the Peace of this Kingdom are expoſed, while the Hopes of a Popiſh Succeſſor, gives Countenance and Encouragement to the Conſpirators in their wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns. And conſidering alſo the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet and Dreadful Apprehenſions of Your good Subjects, by reaſon of the Miſeries and Miſchiefs which threaten them on all parts; as well from Foreign Powers, as from the Conſpiracies within Your ſeveral Kingdoms, againſt which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48236:7"/>no ſufficient Remedy can be provided but by Your Majeſty and Your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Were extreamly ſurprized at the late Prorogation, whereby the Proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Publick Juſtice of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the making the Proviſions neceſſary for the Preſervation of Your Majeſty, and Your Proteſtant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, hath received an Interruption. And they are the more affected herewith, by reaſon of the Experience they have had of the great Progreſs, which the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned Conſpirators have formerly made in their Deſigns, during the late fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Receſſes of Parliament; But that which ſupports them againſt Deſpair, is the Hopes they derive from Your Majeſties Goodneſs, That Your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention was, and does continue by this Prorogation, to make way for Your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Concurrence with the Counſels of Your Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:48236:7"/>
            <p>And Your Petitioners humbly hope, That Your Majeſty will not take Offence, that Your Subjects are thus Zealous, and even impatient of the leaſt Delay of the long hoped for Security, whilſt they ſee your precious Life invaded, the true Religion undermined, their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and innocent Poſterity likely to be ſubjected to Blood, Confuſion, and Ruine; and all theſe Dangers encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, by reaſon of the late Endeavours of Your Majeſty, and Your Parliament, which have added Provocation to the Conſpirators, but have had little or no Effect towards ſecuring againſt them: And they truſt Your Majeſty will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly accept this Diſcovery and Deſire of their Loyal Hearts to preſerve Your Majeſty, and whatever elſe is dear to them, and to ſtrengthen Your Majeſty againſt all Popiſh and Pernicious Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, which any ill-affected Perſons may preſume to offer.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:48236:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>They do therefore moſt humbly Pray, That Your Majeſty will be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly pleaſed (as the only means to quiet the Minds, and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh the Fears of Your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant People, and prevent the eminent Dangers which threaten Your Majeſties Kingdoms, and particularly this Your Great City, which hath already ſo deeply ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for the ſame) to permit Your ſaid Parliament to Sit, from the Day to which they are Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued, until by their Counſels and Endeavours thoſe good Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies ſhall be provided, and thoſe juſt Ends attained, upon which the Safety of Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Perſon, the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, the Peace and Settlement of Your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and the Welfare of this
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48236:8"/>Your Ancient City, do ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely depend. For the purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and obtaining of which good Effects, Your Petitioners una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly do offer their Lives and Eſtates.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>And ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
